[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You cannot see remaining alive.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the body, the material aspect, the fleshy aspect, the rūpa, gets deformed, destroyed.
[SPEAKER_04]: They cannot remain in any consciousness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's how you recognize that then your eye, your nose, your ears are that ultimate away from you, that you just have obviously been appropriating for so long, and it's so close that you can't see it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, you just assume it's in you, it's yours, and you are the result.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it's kind of the expression of you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you start to see that, when you think about... people think about the eye, it is the certain expectation that they will find the real eye somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you won't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thoughts you have about the eye are all you can have about the eye.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because eye itself, it's always going to be ultimate, negative.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what appears is that because of which there is sort of appearance and that's determined by that I.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even you think I, you have to stop regarding that as a real I or as a non-real I or as a both real or not real.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can just recognize I can only have thoughts that stay, that stand in place of an I.
[SPEAKER_04]: And when I say an I, that's another thought that stands in the place of an I, which is another thought, which is another thought.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can never access the I.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can only be a second, sort of, to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whatever thought, whatever abstraction, whatever is going to be secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's all it's necessary to recognize that, because then you see, oh, by being inaccessible, you cannot even conceive ownership of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And by that, can you even access thoughts?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, if you start
[SPEAKER_04]: Refining that principle further...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it's relatively refined when it comes to body.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same principle when it comes to mind, but it's much harder to see, as the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because putuṣa can get rid of the body...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, do you think...
[SPEAKER_04]: If you extend the same principle, then you realize that thoughts themselves, in their nature, arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_04]: You, you sort of manage them, you intend upon them, but then you realize that that intention is secondary to the arising of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Thus, intention shares the same nature of cannot be owned, because it's founded upon things that are inaccessible to ownership.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's how the mind gets free from the subtlest concealings, and becomes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then you can think, and will, and still not own it, while you're willing, and thinking, and deciding, and telling off, and whatever else arahants do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, normally, in a way.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same principle, but it's much harder to see it on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you see it on the level of the body, thoroughly, then, yes, it's far from impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's you spilling over.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same sense that Atavada spills over the five aggregates and owns them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Once that's gone, well, then you still have perceptions in regard to the sense bases that spill over, that assume the access to the eye, to the nose, hence the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the only benefit of sensual sights, that benefit can only pertain to the fleshy eye.
[SPEAKER_04]: Nothing else can benefit from sight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Skin and the sense of touch can only benefit from touching things.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't access that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But by fully assuming access to the body, to the eyes, you are then drawn by that which these things want.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, you think you are accessing all the external sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are touching pleasant objects.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are tasting pleasant sounds.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sorry, pleasant tastes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you are hearing agreeable sounds.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Ear is hearing the sounds.
[SPEAKER_04]: Cannot be different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Eye is seeing the sights.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you, when you say I, you assume the I.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hence, you are pulled by the sights.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why the mindfulness, this mindfulness that I'm talking about, peripheral or letting it endure, is necessary, because you'll never see a connection between your thoughts about the I, your sights, and that
[SPEAKER_04]: Indirect, fleshy organ that is simultaneously present, because of which all of this is possible, that in return defines that which is an I.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why the sense base is defined by the sense object.
[SPEAKER_04]: In itself, you can't even conceive the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if the mindfulness is developed in the way we were talking yesterday, you will be able to hold a thought
[SPEAKER_04]: of the present organ of an eye, because of which I'm thinking of an eye and doing all of this without lapsing, without either jumping too much onto the external notion of what eye is, or thinking of it, you know, eye is this, eye is in me, I am, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're able to see both ends without, kind of, sort of, snapping towards one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: If the mindfulness is developed to the extent necessary, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you know, like a rubber band, sort of, you stretch, you stretch.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it's either going to sort of snap from this end or from this end.
[SPEAKER_04]: You won't be able to kind of include both ends.
[SPEAKER_04]: And both ends are included through development, through discernment of enduring, endurance of the simultaneous theories and two things, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it could be simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_03]: For that, you basically need mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without mindfulness, you cannot do anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: With mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_04]: It does not necessarily bring knowledge, unless you know what you're supposed to know.
[SPEAKER_04]: But certainly, without it, there is absolutely no basis for any discernment.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you already have discernment, then all you need is the practice of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_04]: And satipaṭṭhāna is enough for somebody with the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the only way that will lead to full purification of the being and anything else.
[SPEAKER_04]: As it will describe.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because what else would lead to the full purification?
[SPEAKER_04]: Then just sticking to that clear vision and developing it to the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I've thought about from time to time is the assumption of that something...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's in the context of what Ananda says, the I is better than the world, which one is deeper than the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always the assumption that, you know, there's visions, but there's also something behind that point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you assume that spatiality with the assumption that there's a spatial kind of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am here and things are elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can't stop that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But when you do have such thoughts, you start including them in that proper mindfulness of knowing that all of that is possible, because there is the actual operating flesh of an I, that you also know at the time that that's your thought in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's an accurate thought, because it doesn't conceive it anymore as that hidden entity in the hidden.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when they think of there, they think in some terms of, like, a further yonder.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Instead of seeing that both are possible because there is already there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what... that's the basis of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_04]: That there... Nope.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do think it's so often misconceived.
[SPEAKER_02]: The mindfulness of breathing, watching, you know, watching breaths, you can... you know that the body's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is... this breath is happening.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why the breathing is tāyāsandhāra, it's bound with body.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just inconceivable, one without the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't feel.
[SPEAKER_04]: The body is there when the breathing is there.
[SPEAKER_04]: The breathing is there when the body is there.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they're not the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then that body...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're just looking at one aspect of the body...
[SPEAKER_04]: While the breathing is there, then the body can be manifested as the body, as the feeling, as the thoughts, as any other thing within the principle of two simultaneously present things while you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can focus on both the aspects of bereavement.
[SPEAKER_04]: But still not see the actual relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, but you can't keep focusing on that breath, but you've got to see what relationship you have.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why it's... Yeah, it's completely unnecessary to be focusing on anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It actually takes you away.
[SPEAKER_02]: But just, you can use the breath as one of those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just...
[SPEAKER_02]: Steady is steady.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's their vision, their mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: The intention to breathe in the mind is in the actual, all actual breathing in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you look at their intention to breathe slowly, their intention is there, but this particular breath goes slowly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's beyond mind control.
[SPEAKER_02]: All this, this pleasurable, well, experience of breath,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you start including your volition.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it doesn't start introducing ignorance.
[SPEAKER_04]: The volition usually comes from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you feel.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, whenever you will, you engage in the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I choose to breathe slowly, because that's already there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a given possibility, based on the simultaneity of the present act of breathing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_04]: I choose to, and then you realize that I choose to, is already because of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then you stop adhering to it, as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Description I always run into when you say, like, there's control and a lack of control.
[SPEAKER_04]: When you fully get rid of the slightest assumption of control, outside of the lack of control, to a tiny degree or something, then you fully stop the assumption of any external entity that controls it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it seems that the agents say that the will is not necessary for this sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can be completely paralyzed and still consider your body to be your body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the will of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's ultimately mind, speech, body.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how the will is manifest.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why the action is three times the action.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, you can be paralyzed, but you can still be very much willing to bring your mind perpetuating the same type of mistake all to itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, it's as this stops being usable, because it's gone, but it's still more necessarily... That's why a paralyzed person does not automatically become an Arhat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because he remains ignorant just on a different level now.
[SPEAKER_04]: He cannot express his ignorance in a bodily way on the path.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if he can still speak,
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if, in theory, say, you lose everything, it won't result in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: It will result in the rebirth of another being affected with a vision.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you need to do that while you're alive.
[SPEAKER_04]: Get the mind out of that self-centredness, so to speak, that sense of I am, and then the rebirth cannot affect you.
[SPEAKER_02]: In this suicide, you can't actually kill the body.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, for another hand, like, for example, he can't kill himself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Only acts can sort of prevent body from further, sort of, existing.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not a suicide.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suicide is when the self-centered person, well, attempts to kill himself.
[SPEAKER_04]: And kill himself by killing the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you can't kill yourself directly.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can just kill your body in a real second, kill your body, and then you wait for death to come.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, the death of the body comes from a complete direction which you don't have access to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you don't even... yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why you kill the body, hoping that it will result in death, because that's what you've seen happens.
[SPEAKER_04]: But when death does come, it doesn't come from the way of you kill the body, it comes from the way of the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what death is.
[SPEAKER_04]: It comes from way behind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why putusas are always swept with the death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, always swept with the flood.
[SPEAKER_04]: Swept.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it just comes from behind and takes you where you don't even see it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But for an ārahant, who has developed that direction of death, that direction of not adhering to anything, seeing impermanence and everything, basically seeing that nothing is his, when things do get swept away, he's not there to be swept with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And he is absolutely inconceivable to fear death, because it's not death for him at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's another assumption that, you know, when you see somebody, I don't know, a shot in the head, and you think, ah, they're dead.
[SPEAKER_04]: Their body is gone, in terms of its functionality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But from their point of view, mentally, death
[SPEAKER_04]: Might be lasting much, much longer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Once the body is killed, that's what death says.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we all assume, automatically, based on the observation, that it's instantaneous.
[SPEAKER_04]: But whenever the Buddha wanted to emphasize that the extensive pains, he would say pains like those of dying or death.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you realize, oh, okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Probably it's one thing that body dies instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_04]: And once that happens,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, the experience of that begins.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's horrible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Spare for the mind that they... See, there is...
[SPEAKER_03]: I think... Look, there is the feeling terminating with breathing, and there is another feeling terminating with the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I don't remember that, but, eh... Hey, we were still breathing, but still alive, and then...
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see, I see, like, terminating of life, or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, then... Are you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, we were still alive.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's, that's the one that can last for...
[SPEAKER_03]: Probably quite a while.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, imagine part of your brain somewhere on the floor and still feeling...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you have... you have been sort of withdrawn from... because it was destroyed, the sixth sense base, the perceptions.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't have these accesses anymore of eyes, nose and stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, you're just being sort of crushed from... from everywhere, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind is dying in itself, running.
[SPEAKER_04]: And
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, there's another sutra where it says, like, that the sotāpanna, based on his insight, he can become an arahant while he, like... Again, that's commentary on the moment of death, like the mind moment of death.
[SPEAKER_04]: The moment of death, it's the extent of the experience of death that can endure.
[SPEAKER_04]: For how long?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: So sotāpanna can become an arahant during that time, which now, when you think about it, makes sense, actually, because it's not instantaneous.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a period of complete crushing destruction of the five aggregates that he has full understanding of.
[SPEAKER_04]: What's going to result in full dispassion?
[SPEAKER_04]: There is nowhere for him to adhere, to distract himself from.
[SPEAKER_04]: All he has left is his right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he can easily become an arahant in a moment of death.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said, if he doesn't become an arahant while he's dying, basically, mentally, he can become an arahant while he's in interval.
[SPEAKER_04]: When he's neither there nor born yet, then he can become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_04]: The third type is upon landing.
[SPEAKER_04]: There was a translation.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then he can become an arahant in that next life or then eventually in the seven lives.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you realize it's not seven.
[SPEAKER_04]: He can become an arahant at any time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Up to seven.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, up to seven.
[SPEAKER_04]: But these kind of intervals in between and stuff, you realize this whole notion of I'm alive, I'm alive, moment of death, I'm born again, die, born again.
[SPEAKER_04]: The interval can be an eon before you were born again.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hence the sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have no idea how long you'd be dying.
[SPEAKER_01]: A very, very long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that kind of assumption that it's like, you know, like, people speculate about, like, rebirth and stuff, like, someone died in 1973, this baby was born in 1973, it might have been the rebirth of that person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's fully based on a, gratuitously based on an external perception of death, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: the kind of just switching of the body.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's all you can see.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you never experience yourself differently to be able to tell that actually it's not just that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's in the similar way like with being born.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot really say when the person is born.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you can.
[SPEAKER_03]: You only know that someone is pregnant and then some baby comes out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the process is already paid with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: One point you don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because imagine, like, in a medical school, you know, you, in a, in a, like, in a Czech Republic, the abortion is legal after three months.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the USA.
[SPEAKER_03]: But imagine if, eh, it actually, it's a real human being.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you are just the whole life, seeing them as a doctor.
[SPEAKER_04]: The thing is, that Chinese friend of yours, yeah, he was there, but the thing is, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Even though... say, even if you're not... because the Buddha said when the human being does kind of descend, which is when embryo is formed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, already the conceiving of embryo means conceiving of life.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: They dismiss that because it's just an embryo, just a cell.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, they can arbitrarily decide, oh, three months, it's a...
[SPEAKER_04]: However, even when you do abortion of a fetus, of a one-month-old, you are cutting a body inside.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how they do abortion.
[SPEAKER_04]: You start chopping it inside and then pulling parts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Two months!
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not fetus-formed, yet you still see little arms and stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or recognize, oh, this is... this is an arm.
[SPEAKER_04]: This would have been an arm in a week.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's already an arm.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even people who kind of medically sort of adopt their view have a certain heavy amount of denial that this is just... this is not a living being I'm killing.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's after the third month that he becomes alive.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's completely stupid.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think they focus on the, you know, we're giving the woman the choice aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: They focus on like, oh, this is my job.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not my fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where they give the justification of, oh, you know, this person was raped horribly and got pregnant.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a moral kind of abortion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can, you can kind of sympathize with it almost.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but you can be quite a serious killer.
[SPEAKER_03]: It'd be like a hundred, ten hundred, so... Yeah, well, in China, one child...
[SPEAKER_02]: They have one-child policy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, imagine how many get pregnant second time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: She was doing like a... in the height of... some days.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was something ridiculous, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have memory of saying thirty in one day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thirty a day?
[SPEAKER_02]: They say it was ten.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in a month...
[SPEAKER_02]: You've killed 300 people.
[SPEAKER_04]: Imagine that coming.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, she said she would sleep at night and just have these visions of, after a while, of blood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Babies.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's... she said, no, but it's okay, because they do a chanting after.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the nurses, they get together, each mother, and they do some chanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like some boy is chanting, and the girl comes next.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they know, very well, like, this is... something's wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they're chanting.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why they're singing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's, yeah, loads, loads.
[SPEAKER_02]: Think about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe a hundred people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thousands, thousands.
[SPEAKER_02]: One after a year.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's quite... And the Christians in America, some wrongly, but they still recognize that it's not a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they go too far and say, let's kill the abortion doctors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they kill the doctors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember reading about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get the bombings of it and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: The name of God's moral will forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's so hard to...
[SPEAKER_04]: But it is a useful reflection as well, to stop associating death with the death of the body, and see something that comes from the ultimate inside, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same sense, you can't conceive the sense organs, their direction, you can't access them, you're just because of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, death sweeps them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means you have no... you can't have a relationship with death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it doesn't come from any direction that you can possibly conceal.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you can also, basically, we should say that, you know, because it's nāmarūpa, it goes together, they die together.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even if you, like, say the bullet comes, goes through your head...
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not the only rūpa.
[SPEAKER_03]: But still you have other parts of the body which are... You don't have any parts of the body.
[SPEAKER_04]: There is a body, on the basis of the general rūpa, on the basis of which there can be a consciousness.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, when this body is destroyed, that wasn't your body upon which you were really existing.
[SPEAKER_04]: That was just a more particular manifestation of the form upon which your consciousness was existing.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why you can transcend your body.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can fly out of your body.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why, if you die with ignorance, you get another body.
[SPEAKER_04]: You get another particular manifestation of the same form that you...
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's another important thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: The form that you depend upon now, that you're bound with, rūpa, is the same one you depended upon previous life, and previous life, and previous life, and previous life, despite having different bodies and different particular forms.
[SPEAKER_04]: The nature of the five aggregates remains the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the Buddha said that even if a monk recollects one past life, five hundred of them, all he recollects is these five aggregates, or one among them more particularly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That always remains the basis.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's because, again, people think this is the journey.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're just passing from this life into that.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is always what's present, has always been present.
[SPEAKER_04]: In that ultimate sense, the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's basically... That's why you keep remembering
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not because you keep traveling.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because you keep holding on to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now, the stuff you're holding is the stuff you've been holding beginninglessly for billions of eons of time.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's right here, right now, can be freed from, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a kālika.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, again, people have the linear assumption of death, rebirth, elsewhere, and this, and it's a journey, and you can't... No.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why if you stop associating death with that kind of movement, you realize, ah, death, basically, death doesn't take away the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: It takes away your dependence upon the particular manifestation of the senses of the five aggregates and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all you have to do to be free from death, but really, is free yourself from your senses, and then, eventually, from the conceit in regard to the ideas, and you'll be free from death.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you'll be free from rebirth.
[SPEAKER_04]: From this very same present principles we were talking about, of mindfulness and simultaneous presence,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not, you know, above it, or below, or later, or before.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's how you cannot possibly be affected when illness affects the body, breaking apart, death, loss of limbs, loss of senses, which is... which were not in that particular manifestation of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why, also, when we were talking the other day about madness, like, if the body starts losing the balances and doing things that are not... they're weird, you wouldn't have a personal problem with it, because it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_04]: If there was wisdom, if there was knowledge properly established, you just... Like with Ajahn Chah, like, oh, Ajahn, you're actually not making sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: He stopped engaging in that kind of outlet of speech.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not yours to begin with, so it's not an issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: You couldn't possibly be denying it or having a problem with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: If everybody says, oh, that's, that's... yeah, yeah, that's how this body is acting now.
[SPEAKER_03]: And can this happen to arahants?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I think that... Well, like, say, lose his mind, that out of order he would look like a mad person.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think, theoretically, it could.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that doesn't mean... Well, it can never be compromised.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, externally, he could be mad.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, say, that man disappears and people tell him he was mad.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: He would probably already know that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And he wouldn't have an issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Again, same with that child.
[SPEAKER_04]: He didn't realize because of the stroke.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was thinking one thing and wanting to...
[SPEAKER_04]: He was thinking he was saying one thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was saying something completely different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Completely, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: But there should be, like, in that arahant, some emotions should be missing, like fear or... All of that is missing.
[SPEAKER_04]: He cannot be afraid.
[SPEAKER_04]: He can suffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because he's not afraid of death.
[SPEAKER_04]: How can he be afraid of losing the speech, mind and bodily activities?
[SPEAKER_04]: Could not be his concern.
[SPEAKER_04]: What he cannot lose is the... is that purified, freed point of view.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even if madness becomes his reality, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: But even that reality is equally affected
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he might not be able to express it anymore, because the speech is slurring, the chemicals in brain that were helping perception just don't work anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: They're perceiving things differently and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is his reality.
[SPEAKER_03]: But still, he would not engage, like, in unwholesome activities, basically, like, attacking people, or being aggressive, or this thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would be just mad, and...
[SPEAKER_04]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because aggressive behavior is not necessarily
[SPEAKER_04]: There is the sign of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the more serious issue, it's not aggressive behavior, it's denial of when these things were pointed out.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's that kind of almost conceited refusal.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I cannot get mad.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm not mad.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's an issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if he was punching people in the face before that, that might not necessarily be an issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same sense, there was that Arahant who was like, oops, like the whole province got upset at monks because he was rude.
[SPEAKER_04]: Really abrasive, telling people off, just calling other monks shavings.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just horrible.
[SPEAKER_04]: And people complained to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the Buddha called him.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was a big issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the Buddha saw he was actually an arahant, fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_04]: But he was reborn... he had a habit, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was reborn, like, over 500 lifetimes in a high Brahmin family.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I think he was not so rude, actually.
[SPEAKER_03]: I read that story.
[SPEAKER_03]: He was only called them, like, a... Well, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what this...
[SPEAKER_04]: The story would always condense the meaning and say he called them shavings.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_04]: If the point came when the whole area complained to the Buddha, and the Buddha had to call him for that,
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, he wouldn't have, like, one monk got upset.
[SPEAKER_04]: He called me a sheveling, and then the Buddha summoned him and said, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was a big issue, because he was going around doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And people said, what the kind of monk is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can extrapolate, relatively accurately, that actually, it was probably in many ways.
[SPEAKER_03]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then the Buddha said, no, he was just, he was used to talking down to people.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was doing it without ill will.
[SPEAKER_04]: How he can punch someone in the face... No, I just said that in theory.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you're madness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you really, you don't...
[SPEAKER_04]: The way your perception got messed up with the chemicals in your brain and everything else, you don't necessarily perceive him as a human anymore, and you hit him.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hit it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then afterwards, they tell you, you punched this monk in the face.
[SPEAKER_04]: You would not be denying.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's my whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like a transparent person,
[SPEAKER_04]: which is the basis of wisdom, transparency, base of mindfulness, would not be denying it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if the most horrible stuff, so to speak, you wouldn't be able to deny it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you wouldn't have a reason to deny it because it's not personal.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not personal.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why... that's why you wouldn't... you don't have... that's why Arahant is, as in private, so in public, in terms of his behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: He has no, like, oh, this is...
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, when people sometimes regard personally some weird stuff, that's actually if somebody... well, it's nothing personal.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's nothing like you need to hide about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would you be hiding that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And most people do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Most people, like lay people out there, have a lot of stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: That it's kind of, you know... Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's taken personally.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the sole reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's more of an issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not the actual manifestation of behavior.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, you know, even in the Vinaya rules, often, often, if somebody's possessed with the madness, he's exempt.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means he could have done serious offenses, but it was a genuine madness.
[SPEAKER_04]: It means it wasn't his intentional doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, say, if he does something to a woman, rapes a woman,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, his point of view was not involved, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: His individual was not doing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, if when that's done, it's just this full-on, you know, rude or aggressive denial, and like, no, no, I and beyond all of that, then it's just like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, that's not madness speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it shows, basically, some clinging is there.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's some notion, it's some idea of yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the definition of conceit.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or even if, say, you know, like people say you're mad, you can't agree on the terminology.
[SPEAKER_04]: Say, well, I wasn't mad, it was Yakash possessed my mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because maybe you see those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if people say, well, yeah, you were mad, you wouldn't be arguing upon it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, yeah, that's how you can call madness, sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it wasn't... it doesn't... it doesn't affect your personal image, unless there is an image that you hold personal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you're shitting, pissing yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, the body does that.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_04]: The body not being yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, it can happen to anyone, anytime.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: You are not sure that tomorrow you will not... Well, it's when you get encephalitis and you suddenly turn into a completely different person.
[SPEAKER_04]: But your point of view can never go down, if he has developed wisdom, because it's independent of the content of the... of the quickness of the intellect.
[SPEAKER_04]: All it needs is the presence of things.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So you can be... you can become stupid, you can have a stroke, you can... all sorts of things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that dimension, it remains completely unaffected.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I was, you know, being rough with people for 30 years of my life, maybe before, that habit is strong.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you know, OK, I calm down, I become arrogant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if things start, you know, start getting mad, that habit might kick back in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's been done much longer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's just the way it's been growing so far.
[SPEAKER_04]: But as I said, the point of view that has been purified, it has no ill will there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the relationship of, like, with the eye, for example, you know, I can think of an image of my eye, kind of things.
I assume it applies just on a much more subtle level to the mano and dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can think of some vague notion of what the mind
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, mind is a sense base defined by the dhamma that you think.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's negative in regard to that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's... yeah, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, when you do have a thought about that negative particular thing, when you realize that there is a negative in particular thought, you want to make sure that the thought about your mind does not conceive
[SPEAKER_04]: Itself, as actually, this is what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Mind and this.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't confuse yourself that you're thinking about your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what you have to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like to figure it out or to catch it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just to stop misconceiving it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the whole point of the whole Mūla Paryāya Sūtra.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, maybe we can only say that mind is only that which can think thoughts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly why, yeah, that's why you can free your mind from appropriation.
[SPEAKER_04]: You appropriate it when you misconceive it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's there anyway, anyhow, on its own, by itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's exactly the reason why you can become liberated.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, you know, you can, you know, you can tell, you can kind of say to anyone, you know, like, I just hear things are yonder, and you're like, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you go to the mind, then they kind of assume it's all... Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no yonder.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, then the confusion really takes over, and then they tend to
[SPEAKER_04]: Stop the thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: That level.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's a here and yonder in the mind, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is more negative than anything else, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can conceive the thinker.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you conceive the seer, you conceive the hearer.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly why, even if your senses are taken away from you, the conceit still remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is perhaps going a little bit away from, you know, a dhamma principle thing, but I think it's interesting and important to think about just because of how often it's brought up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to say, like, you know, people study neurochemistry, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to say that it's like there is no effect on particular things because of things in the range that people go too far and assume that
[SPEAKER_04]: People go too far, basically, and then they ascribe their point of view and their responsibility to that in the brain.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_04]: The results, the chemicals in the brain can present you with things, but it's on you, basically, to keep maintaining ignorance in regard to the reasoned things, or knowledge in regard to the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: Same with the eyes.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, there are chemicals and hormones.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But people say that as if, like, oh, it's because of it, not because I've chosen to do so.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, they say that correlation is not causation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Causation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, definitely correlated.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking back to the days of when I used to take antidepressants.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can kind of see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like things presented themselves in a perhaps more pleasing way, you know, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can't treat depression as a state of mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can only kind of... so that then you can make choices that will take you out of depression.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not how medicine is presented.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's presented as treatment of such-and-such state.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: One last one for me, just because I've read it so many times and I just never really understood what it meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a lot of times
[SPEAKER_01]: In the suttas, where it's like, the Buddha mentions that he and his disciples, like, you know, they don't get into arguments and quarrels in terms of views and stuff like that, especially in the new sutta-nipāta translation that comes up a lot, like, you know, engaging in disputes and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm having trouble, like, I guess, understanding that, well, at the same time, understanding that there is right things and wrong things.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that, that refers to his disciples, which means, refers to the noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which means, that's all he, that's all he put into words.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's, I, I, that, I wasn't...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, so that's the point, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: They might be disagreeing in a particular interpret, or explanation, description of something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, fundamentally, if these two people both partake in the right view, they will have to agree.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like internal, not external, kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even externally, it cannot result in an actual dispute.
[SPEAKER_01]: An external of the noble Saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not getting into an argument with some random Brahmin with weird views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think...
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: You read it yourself, but I thought it's referring to the internal, to the actual... His disciples among themselves are not arguing like other sects.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you see that in other suttas, when they praise, and I see your disciples always in concord, always sort of
[SPEAKER_04]: Sharing the same, same views, same take on it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Unlike when I go there, they're arguing, attacking the teacher.
[SPEAKER_04]: I say this, you say that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you have the book here?
[SPEAKER_03]: But you know, I don't know what impression I...
[SPEAKER_04]: But either way, either way, they cannot argue among themselves.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: If they have a view, nor will they go into an actual dispute with somebody else on account of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if another person comes, asks
[SPEAKER_04]: They give a teaching, they disagree, like, it's absolutely not my problem, and certainly not me, or nothing that I need to defend or convince you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, oh, even when the Buddha was teaching something, it's like, no, they would shake their head in disapproval and say, well, yes, okay, master, go tell my go, and the Buddha couldn't care less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, why did he say, oh, he didn't, he didn't accept what I said, he didn't believe me.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he would go to another people who kind of approve of his view, and then, they all...